Guide to the George Barker Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George Barker collection
1933-1967
GEN MSS 858
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.84
(2 boxes)
The collection consists of poetry and prose by George Barker in autograph, typescript, and printed forms, including poems with autograph revisions by T. S. Eliot. Also present are a small group of letters to Barker from editors and colleagues including Brian Higgins and Oscar Williams, six line drawings by Barker, and a collection of ten typescripts of poems by William Bell.
Barker, George, 1913-1991
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from C. A. Stonehill on the E. J. and F. W. Beinecke Rare Book Endowment Fund, 1967.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
George Barker (1913-1991)
George Granville Barker (1913-1991), English poet and author.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of poetry and prose by George Barker in manuscript, typescript, and printed forms, including poems with autograph revisions by T. S. Eliot. Also present are a small group of letters to Barker from editors and colleagues including Brian Higgins and Oscar Williams, six line drawings by Barker, and a collection of ten poems by William Bell.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Writings, 1933-1967. II. Correspondence, 1934-1965. Series III. Other Papers, undated.
Authors, English -- 20th Century; English literature -- 20th Century; Poets, English -- 20th Century; Drawings (visual works) -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; Authors -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; Poets -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; Auden, W. H. (Wystan Hugh), 1907-1973; Barker, George, 1913-1991; Bell, William, 1924-1948; Eliot, T. S. (Thomas Stearns), 1888-1965; Gascoyne, David, 1916-2001; Higgins, Brian, 1930-1965; Williams, Oscar, 1900-1964
- Writings, 1933-1967; Series I; 26
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into four subseries: Poetry, Prose, Proof Sheets, and Printed Material.
  - Poetry
    - "A View from the Blind", circa 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Autograph manuscript pages of poems used in or gathered for the book.
    - Fourteen poems, circa 1960-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Autograph and typescript drafts of poems.
    - "The New Anadyomene", 1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Autograph manuscript, revised, of a twenty-four line poem, accompanied by a typed letter, signed, from Derek Verschoyle accepting the poem for publication.
    - Draft of poem, circa 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Autograph draft beginning "Ichor-pressing my hands whence flow / Liquids of the spirit's fruit" with pencilled note by Barker: "Poem written about 1937."
    - Poems published in News of the World, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Typescripts (11 p.) of three poems: "To My Son," "News of the World," and "Turn on Your Side and Bear the Day to Me," with revisions by T. S. Eliot.
    - "The Seraphina", circa 1957 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Mimeographed typescript (63 p.) for internal use at British Broadcasting Company, with Barker's pencilled autograph revisions; also an additional two pages of brief autograph notes concerning the play.
    - "The Golden Epodes", circa 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
      Two octavo notebooks containing 235 pages of Barker's autograph drafts of lyrics; also present are two pencil drawings and 7 pages of typescript drafts.
    - "The Golden Epodes", 1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Corrected typescript with autograph revisions, variant autograph drafts of 37 lyrics, and a typed title page.
    - "Elegiacs for T. S. Eliot", circa 1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Autograph draft (7 p.)
    - "The Sisteron", 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Autograph manuscript (70 p.) in a notebook; also present are notes for lectures, teaching schedules, and "Notes on Michelangelo."
    - Four poems, circa 1966 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Autograph and typescript versions of the poems "Lake Erie," "Pan Am Flight 462 Jan. 14 1966," "Inscription for the Gazebo at York University," and "Dupe Eatherly."
  - Prose
    - "Notes on the Function of Metaphor", undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Autograph manuscript (7 p.)
    - "Ansi toute poesie est elegie", circa 1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Carbon typescript of a translation into French by David Gascoyne of an essay by Barker; signed by Barker and Gascoyne, with a brief explanatory typescript note by Barker. The original essay was titled "Therefore All Poems are Elegies."
      Accompanied by pages 9-12 only of a typescript radio talk (in French) possibly broadcast in the BBC Overseas Service, discussing Barker's "The View from a Blind I." Approximately 1-1/2 pages are devoted to a critical assessment of the book, the remainder to a French translation of the poem "I Walked by a Window in Ireland," followed by the original English text. At the foot of page 12 is a pencilled note by Barker to "David" asking for a translation.
    - "Deaner Notes May MCMLX", 1959, circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Typescript notes dated May 27 and June 1 (1965?), apparently a fragment of a diary, together with another 4 pages of typed notes of an autobiographical nature.
    - Answers to a questionnaire on Dante, recorded for a BBC program, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Typescript, signed, with autograph revisions; accompanied by a typed note from BBC Drama Department returning the script.
    - Introduction to Brian Higgins' The Northern Fiddler, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Two autograph versions, one draft in pencil, one in red ink; the latter is the closest to the published text.
    - "A Little Panegyric for the 60th Birthday of Wystan Auden", 1967 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Autograph draft (5 pages) and corrected typescript, signed and dated "York 1967," of material for the third BBC program.
    - "The Memoirs of Lord B: notes for autobiography", undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Autograph manuscript (31 pages) and corrected typescript (1 page). Together with 5 pages of photocopied sheets of "Speculative Synopsis of the Autobiography of Lord B" inscribed to Seymour Lawrence and signed by Barker, with one original typescript page.
  - Proof Sheets
    - Alanna Autumnal, 1933, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Galley proofs with autograph corrections, annotations, and additions, with an autograph letter, signed, from his editor at Wishart & Company.
    - Dreams of a Summer Night, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Advance proof sheets with autograph revisions.
  - Printed Material
    - George Barker, Martin Bell, Charles Causley, Penguin Modern Poets 3 (Harmondsworth, England: Penguin Books Ltd., 1962) (Box 2, Folder 22)
      First edition containing twenty-three poems by Barker; signed by Barker on the title page, inscribed by him to "Rose" on page 11, and with autograph notes on each poem on their pages.
    - A View from a Blind (London: Faber and Faber, 1962) (Box 2, Folder 23)
      First edition, signed by Barker; contains autograph notes, corrections, dates, and other observances throughout.
    - Moments of Truth (London: Keepsake Press, 1965) (Box 2, Folder 24)
      First edition; Barker is represented by "Autobiograpical [sic] Footnote" which has an autograph correction and an inscription: "G.B. to L.C.R. 1965."
    - Poetry, volume 105, number 5 (February 1965) (Box 2, Folder 25)
      Contains Barker's "Formal Elegy on the Death of Oscar Williams" with autographs corrections and annotations.
    - Poems, 1953-1965, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
      Five leaves cut from periodicals, each bearing a poem by Barker, and each with autograph explanatory notes.
- Correspondence, 1934-1965; Series II; 9
  Series II is organized into two subseries: Letters from Barker, Letters to Barker.
  - Letters from Barker
    - Autograph draft to David Higham, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Three letters, autograph and typed letters, signed, to his sister "Otto" (Mrs. John Frye), 1962 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Typed letter, signed, to William Butler Yeats, 1937 Apr 9 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Typed draft letter to Secretary of the Overseas Manpower Committee, 1945 July 13 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Letters to Barker
    - Faber Faber, 1937-1957 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Higgins, Brian, 1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Pearn, Pollinger Higham, Ltd., 1949, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Williams, Oscar, 1956-1965 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - General correspondence, 1934-1958 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Other Papers, undated; Series III; 2
  The series contains one folder of line drawings by Barker and one folder of poems by William Bell.
  - Drawings, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Six line drawings in graphite and ink on paper and cardboard.
  - Poems, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    Typescripts of unsigned poems bearing a title page "Ten Anonymous Elegies." They are accompanied by a typed note, signed, by Barker: "These poems, which were sent anonymously to me in 1943, I belive [sic] to be the work of the young poet William Bell, who died in 1948. His one published book Mountains beneath the Horizon, was published by Faber & Faber."